《博物馆奇妙夜》
Hey，watch it.
喂！小心点
（故障 这招没用）
Oh，come on.
不会吧
Hey，Mike！
嘿 麦克
- Hey，Larry。- How you doing？
- 拉瑞 - 你好吗？
Have you seen Nicky？
尼克呢？
I'm pretty sure he went with Erica。It was half day today.
他跟雅莉回去了 今天是职场家长日
Parent career Day.
只读半天
（职场家长日）
- Hey。- Hey。Come on in.
- 嘿 - 嘿 进来吧
- You all right？- Yeah，yeah.
- 你还好吧？- 还好
Why didn't anybody tell me it was career Day？
怎么没人跟我说 今天是职场家长日？
What do you mean？Nicky said he was gonna tell you.
什么？尼克说他会告诉你的
Oh，okay，I guess he forgot.
我想他忘了
There he is。How are you，Larry？
他来了 你好吗 拉瑞？
Good。How are you doing，Don？
很好 你呢 唐恩？
Good.
很好
Can you believe this weather？
你说这天气够怪的吧？
Chilly，right？Chilly，chilly，chilly willy the penguin.
冷冰冰 像冷冰冰的酷企鹅
Leave me alone。Hey，why don't I go tell the little corncob you're here.
别吵啦 我会跟小可爱说你来了
Great。Great，that's great。Yeah，thanks.
好 谢了
Wow，your fiance really manages to squeeze a lot onto that belt.
你未婚夫腰上挂的家伙可真多
- Stop it。- What？
- 别闹了 - 什么？
What？No，it's like he's…
什么？我是说 他就好像…
…the Batman of stockbrokers.
股票市场的武林至尊
- Bond trader。- Bond trader。Sorry.
- 他是债券交易员 - 债券交易员 抱歉
Hey，how's it going with that virtual-reality driving range that you wanted to open？
你的虚拟高球练习场进度如何？
Getting there，still waiting for the technology to catch up.
技术面还有待克服
It's not easy，there are a lot of moving parts.
这不简单 有很多移动的物品
Hey，do you think Nick would like Queens？
你想尼克会喜欢皇后区吗？
Oh，no，Larry。You didn't get evicted again，did you？
噢 不 拉瑞 你不会又被赶出来了吧？
I didn't…
我没有…
…get evicted。I didn't get evicted，no。I mean，I didn't…
被赶出来 我没有 不 我是说…
- No，I didn't get evicted yet。It's like… - Larry，listen to me.
- 不 我还没有被赶出来 - 拉瑞 听我说
I don't know how much more Nicky can take.
尼克不能再忍受这一切了
Every couple months，it's a new career，a new apartment.
每隔几个月就换新工作 新住所
If it wasn't for Nicky，I wouldn't say anything，I would stay out of it.
要不是为了尼克 我不会管你
It's just，it's too much instability。It's not good for him.
这么不安定对他不好
I'm trying to figure things out right now，okay？
我正在设法解决问题
You know…
你要知道
…I don't think that Nicky should stay with you.
我不认为尼克该跟你在一起
- What？- Just until you get really settled.
- 什么？- 除非你安定下来
Hey，Dad.
嘿 爸
- Hey，ready to carve it up？- Cool.
- 准备去冰上溜跶了？- 酷啊
All right，good！Take it，Nicky！Break away！
好耶 尼克 抄球盘！冲出去！
- What are you doing？- Hey，Nicky！Are you all right？
- 你搞什么啊？- 小乖 你还好吧？
- You okay？- I'm fine。Would you get off the ice？
- 你没事吧？- 我很好 你下去好吗？
Listen。Their left defenseman is a very weak skater.
听着 他们的左卫很弱
So you go left side，you got a clear shot at the goal。Okay？
往左去 你就有机会射门 好吗？
- Cool，thanks。- All right，man.
- 谢了 - 好
We're good here。We're good。All right。As you were，skaters.
没事 我们很好 继续比赛吧
Game on！
加油！
I'm good.
我没事
I'm telling you，you tore it up out there today.
你今天表现得超精彩
Thinking the NHL is a serious possibility.
当职业选手绝对没问题
I don't really wanna be a hockey player anymore.
我不想打曲棍球了
- All right。What do you wanna be？- A bond trader.
- 好吧 那你想做什么？- 债券交易员
A bond trader？
债券交易员？
Yeah，it's what Don does。He took me to his office last week.
唐恩就是做那个的 他带我去过他办公室
That's cool.
好吧
So you wanna dress up in a monkey suit and tie every day？
你想每天穿西装打领带？
Like an automaton robot？
像个机器人？
Trust me，you can't play hockey in a cubicle。Kind of awkward.
办公隔间里不能打球 太窘了
Well，he's got a pretty big office.
他有一间很大的办公室
That's not the point。Come on，you love hockey.
那不是重点 你喜欢曲棍球的
I still like it，but bond trading's my fallback.
我还是喜欢 但当交易员是我的退路
Your fallback？
你的退路？
Wait a minute。You're too young to have a fallback，okay？
等等 你还没大到要有退路
And also，where did you ever even hear that word？
还有你是从哪听到这字眼的？
Mom was talking to Don about all your different schemes.
妈跟唐恩有谈过你的阴谋
She called them schemes？
她说是阴谋？
She said it was time you found a fallback.
她说你该找个退路了
Are you really moving again？
你真的又要搬家了？
I don't know。We'll see。I mean…
我不知道 再说吧
…there's some pretty cool places out in Queens.
皇后区有些地方挺酷的
- Yeah。- Hey.
- 是啊 - 嘿
Hey，Nicky，look at me.
尼克 看着我
Look at me，man。I wanna tell you something.
看着我
I know that things have been kind of up and down for me lately…
我知道我最近状况很多
…and that's been hard for you.
你并不好过
But I really feel like my moment's coming and when it does…
不过我觉得我就快成功了
…everything's just gonna come together，you know？
到那时 一切都会很顺利
What if you're wrong…
万一你弄错了呢？
…and you're just an ordinary guy who should get a job？
万一你只是个 需要找份工作的普通人呢？
All right，well…
这个嘛
You know what，we'll figure it out，okay？
我会搞清楚的 好吗？
All right？Come on，let's get you back to Mom's.
好了 我们去找你妈吧
Mr。Daley，I can honestly say，in 43 years at this agency…
达理先生 我敢说 我从事这行43年
…l've never seen a resume quite like yours.
从未看过你这种履历
All right.
好耶
That wasn't a compliment.
那并不是赞美
It says here you were the cEo…
上面写你当过执行长
…of Snaptime Industries.
叫「啪哒集团」
Care to elaborate on that？
能说明一下吗？
Sure。Well，that was the umbrella corporation for my invention，the Snapper.
当然 那是我发明的出品集团 啪哒弹指器
You know，you snap，the lights come on。Snap，they come off.
弹一下指头 灯就开 弹一下指头 灯就关
Didn't they already make that？
这不是早就上市了？
No，no，that's the clapper，which，obviously…
不 那是拍掌器 那很显然是…
…stole a bit of our thunder.
剽窃了我们的点子
Personally，I don't really see what the big difference is，I mean：
我个人是看不出有什么差别
You know，whatever，but…
你知道 随便 不过
…apparently there is a significant portion of the population that has trouble actually…
不过显然有占很多数比例的人口 这方面有点困难
- …snapping。- Clapping's easier.
- 不大能够弹指头 - 拍掌比较简单
Debatable.
这有待商确
I can't help you.
我帮不了你
Debbie？
黛比？
Can I call you Debbie？Because…
我能叫你黛比吗？
…I felt a connection when I entered this office…
我一进来就觉得你倍感亲切
…and I don't know，I feel like you did too.
我觉得你对我也有同感
I didn't feel a connection.
我对你没感觉
Look.
听着
I need a job tomorrow，okay？
我明天就要有一份工作
If I don't have one…
要是找不到…
well，I just need it，okay？
反正我就是需要 好吗？
Well，I don't know.
我不知道
I might have one thing.
可能有个缺
They've turned down everyone I've sent over there，but…
他们回绝了我派去的每一个人
Great.
太好了
Who knows？
谁知道呢？
You might get lucky.
你可能会走运
- Excuse me。Hi。- Hi.
- 抱歉 你好 - 你好
I'm Larry Daley。I've got a job interview with cecil Fredricks.
我是拉瑞·戴利 我来找克西傅德瑞克面试
- Right。He should still be in his office。- Great.
- 他应该还在办公室里 - 太好了
- I'm Rebecca Hutman。I'm a docent here。- Hi.
- 我是导览员贝嘉贺门 - 你好
- Let me point you in the right direction。- Great.
- 我带你过去吧 - 太好了
Teddy Roosevelt，right？
泰迪罗斯福总统 对吧？
- Yes，a great visionary。- Yes，definitely.
- 对 好眼力 - 当然
He was our 4th president，right？
他是第四任总统 对吧？
- Twenty-sixth。- Twenty-sixth.
- 是第二十六任 - 第二十六任
Please don't touch the exhibits！I mean…
请勿触碰展品
Riffraff.
下等人
Miss Hutman。I cannot tolerate this type of chaos.
贺门小姐 我不能忍受这种混乱
I mean，this is a museum，not a…
这是一间博物馆 不是…
Do you know what 「museum」 means？
你知道博物馆代表什么吗？
It doesn't mean，「Daddy，it's a big Tyrannosaurus thing.
那不是代表 「哇 爸爸 好大的恐龙」
Can I touch its leg？「 No！
「我能碰他的脚吗？」 不行！
Work it out，please.
拜托你解决问题
- Will do，sir。- Thank you.
- 我会的 - 谢谢
Dr。McPhee，the museum director.
麦菲博士 博物馆总监
Seems like a fun guy.
看来挺风趣的
Control your young，please。Can we？
拜托管一下你的小孩
（警卫室）
Hello？Just kidding.
谁啊？开玩笑的啦
Hi。I'm Larry Daley。Are you Mr。Fredricks？
你好 我是拉瑞·戴利 你是傅德瑞克先生？
Mr。Fredricks was my father.
傅德瑞克先生是我爸
I am cecil。Good to meet you，Larry。Nice firm handshake.
我叫克西 幸会 拉瑞 握手力道不错
I like that。Tells a lot about a man。Come on in.
我喜欢 这代表一个人的个性 进来吧
Let's talk turkey here.
我们就打开天窗说亮话吧
The museum is losing money，hand over fist.
博物馆近年亏损连连
I guess kids today don't care about wax figures or stuffed animals.
我猜现在的孩子 不再喜欢蜡像或填充动物了
So they're downsizing，which is code for firing…
所以他们要缩编 就是裁撤…
…myself and the other two night guards.
我和夜班警卫
They want to replace us with one new guard.
他们要找新的警卫来取代我们
- Oh，sorry。- Well，what are you gonna do？
- 抱歉 - 你又能怎样呢？
I'd like you to meet my two colleagues here.
见见我两位同事吧
Reginald？Gus？
雷纳？葛斯？
Where is he？I'll beat him with my fist！
他人呢？我要亲手扁他
Gus，this is Larry Daley，the kid who wants to be the new night guard.
葛斯 这位是拉瑞·戴利 他要来当新的夜班警卫
Night guard？
夜班警卫？
No，the lady at the agency said this was a museum position.
介绍所的人说是博物馆的职位
Most important position in the museum，Larry.
博物馆里最重要的职位
He looks like a weirdie.
他看来像个怪胎
Wonderful guard，terrible people skills.
好警卫 做人却很糟
Now，listen，lunch box。Don't try anything funny.
听着 呆瓜 别想耍花招
I once went nine rounds with John L。Sullivan.
我跟拳王对战过九回合
You never fought John L。Sullivan in your life.
你才没跟拳王对战过
Gentlemen，we have a job candidate here.
两位 这里有个应征者
He's got an excellent resume，a winning attitude…
他的履历很漂亮 态度又积极
…and I say let's give him a shot。What do you say？
我认为该给他一个机会
Hang on a sec。I think I might wanna have a little time just to think it over.
等等 我要想一下
Do you want the job or not，snack shack？
你到底要不要工作 呆瓜？
- No，no，I want the job… - welcome to the night guards，Larry.
- 要 我要这份工作 - 欢迎成为夜班警卫 拉瑞
Larry，meet me up on the second floor.
拉瑞 到二楼等我
I'll slip into my orthopedics and give you a little tour。Arthritic knees.
我穿上护膝带你走一圈 膝盖关节炎
Not fun getting old，my friend。Go on.
年纪大可不好玩 朋友 走吧
You really think he's the one？
你真认为他可以？
Oh，yes.
当然
He's the one.
他可以的
Gotta keep it moving，Larry。I'm pretty spry for an old man.
快跟上 我可是活动力很强的老人
This is the Diorama Room.
这是实景模型陈列区
Oh，yeah.
是啊
I remember these little guys。Cute.
我记得这些小家伙 真可爱
Cecil！
克西
Hey，cecil！
嘿 克西
- Did I get you good？- Yeah.
- 我吓到你了吧？- 是啊
You got me.
你吓到我了
Seriously，though，no fooling around in here。This stuff is really old.
说真的 别在这里干蠢事 这玩意很古老了
All right，then。As you can see，it's pretty quiet in here these days.
好了 你也看得出来 最近很冷清
On the left there is your Attila the Hun.
左边是匈奴王阿提拉和匈奴人
And here we have our Easter Island head.
这里是复活岛的巨石像
Hey，cecil.
嘿
And this，of course，is the Hall of African Mammals.
这里是非洲哺乳动物陈列室
Ah，yes.
是啊
Monkeys。I love monkeys.
猴子 我喜欢猴子
- Yeah。- Guy's cute.
- 是啊 - 他真可爱
Yeah，we call him Dexter。He's quite a little…
是啊 我们叫他德克斯特 他真是…
…ball of fun，aren't you，Dexter？
可爱 对不对啊 德克斯特？
Moving on.
走吧
And，finally，this is the temple of the Pharaoh Ahkmenrah.
最后 这是法老王阿卡曼拉之殿
And in that tomb right down there，the pharaoh himself.
下面那个石棺 法老王就躺里面
Neat.
真有趣
And hanging on the wall behind him…
他后方墙上挂的是
…was his most prized possession，the Tablet of Ahkmenrah.
他最重视的宝贝 阿卡曼拉刻写板
Twenty-four-carat gold。It's worth a fortune.
24K纯金 价值连城
Very cool.
真酷
It is indeed，Larry.
没错
Very cool.
很酷
All right。Report here at 5 tomorrow。We'll walk you through your duties.
明天下午五点报到 我们会跟你说明你的职责
Okay，5。I'll be here.
五点 我会到的
Moving on.
走吧
Hey，it's me。So I got a job.
是我 我找到工作了
Larry，that's great。What is it？
真是太好了 什么工作？
It's a job…
这工作…
…at the Museum of Natural History.
在自然历史博物馆里
Yeah，so you can tell Nicky that we won't be moving.
你可以告诉尼克我们不搬家了
Larry，this is good news.
这是好消息
Yeah，no，definitely。So I'll see you tomorrow？
是啊 明天见了
- Okay。- Okay，bye.
- 好 - 好 再见
Larry？
拉瑞？
Your keys。Your torch.
你的钥匙 手电筒
- Right。- You'll wanna strap those to your belt.
- 好 - 把那些绑在腰带上
It can get a little spooky around here at night…
这里晚上会有点吓人
…so you might wanna put a few lights on.
所以你可能会想开几盏灯
All right，flashlight，keys。What am I for…？
手电筒 钥匙 还有什么
The instruction manual.
指令手册
Instructions.
手册
You start with one，two，three…
依顺序来 一 二 三
Four？
四？
Are you cracking wise？
你是在搞笑吗？
I ought to punch you in the nose，hopscotch.
我真该赏你一拳 臭小子
Leave him alone，Gus。You got it covered，right，Larry？
别闹他了 葛斯 拉瑞 你行吧？
Yeah，yeah，I got it.
我行的
- You better get it！- Gus.
- 你最好是行 - 葛斯
Larry，do them in order，do them all and do them quick.
照顺序来 要彻底也要快
And the most important thing of all to remember：Don't let anything in or out.
还有 最重要的是要记得 别让任何东西进来或出去
Out？
出去？
Good luck，son.
祝你好运 孩子
- Night，Gus。- Young buck。Cracking wise.
- 晚安 葛斯 - 臭小子 爱搞笑
Moving on.
走吧
Hello？
喂？
Hello！
喂！
Check！
检查
Check.
I am Larry.
我是拉瑞
Check！Larry！Larry.
检查 拉瑞 拉瑞…
Monday！Monday！Monday！
星期一！星期一！星期一！
Monster Truck Rally.
超级卡车大赛
Cecil？
克西？
Okay，very funny，cecil！
很好笑 克西
What is this，like a David copperfield thing？
这是什么 大卫魔术秀吗？
This is weird.
这真怪
Cecil？
克西？
Come on。Revolve。Revolve！
快啊 旋转！旋转！
- Name，please？- Cecil…
- 姓名？- 克西
- …Fredricks！- One moment。Connecting.
- 傅德瑞克 - 稍候 拨接中
- Hello。- Cecil！It's Larry Daley！
- 喂 - 克西 我是拉瑞·戴利
Larry。Yes，how can I help you？
拉瑞 有事吗？
The dinosaur… The dinosaur is alive！
恐龙活过来了
I'm having a little trouble hearing you，friend.
我听不见
Tequila.
龙舌兰！
The dinosaur's alive！
恐龙活过来了
What do I do？Tell me what to do！
我该怎么办？
Read the instructions。It explains everything.
看手册 手册里都有解释
Okay，I got them！
我拿到了
- I'll see you tomorrow。- Wait！What…？
- 明天见 - 等等！什么？
（一 丢骨头）
What bone？
什么骨头？
Fetch？
捡骨头？
Play fetch？
玩捡骨头？
No way.
不会吧
- Dum-dum。- Yes？
- 笨笨 - 什么？
- You give me gum-gum。- I give you gum-gum？
- 你给我糖糖 - 给你糖糖？
You new dum-dum。You give me gum-gum.
新笨笨 给我糖糖
Okay，you know what？I have no gum-gum。Sorry.
你知道吗？我没有糖糖 抱歉
And my name isn't dum-dum，my name's Larry.
还有我不叫笨笨 我叫拉瑞
No，your name dum-dum.
不 你叫笨笨
Oh，you in trouble，dum-dum.
你麻烦大了 笨笨
You'd better run-run from Attila the Hun-Hun.
你最好跑跑躲匈匈阿提拉
See you later，dum-dum.
待会见了 笨笨
What is happening？
怎么回事？
Hey.
嘿
How you doing？
你好吗？
Are you…？
你是…
You're…
「Sakagahwahwaya」？
莎卡加味？
You're 「Sakagawaya」？
你是莎卡加味？
Oh，Sakagawea。You're Sakagawea？
莎卡佳薇！你是莎卡佳薇？
The glass。I can't…
玻璃 我不能…
…hear you.
听到你
You can't…？You can't hear me？
你听不到？你听不到我？
Excuse me。「Who assisted the Lewis and clark…」
对不起 你帮助路易斯和克拉克…
Right，so that's Lewis and clark and you're… Right.
那就是路易斯和克拉克？而你是…
You seem… I'm Larry.
你好像… 我是拉瑞
What's going on？What's…？Do you know what's going on here？
怎么回事？你知道这是怎么回事吗？
Huns。I gotta…
匈奴人 我得要…
（二 关好狮子 不然他们会吃了你）
Hey。Hi.
嘿 嗨
Tin Man。Hey。Hi。How you doing？
大铜人 嗨 你好啊
I'm new。It says I'm supposed to lock up the lions or they'll eat me.
我新来的 上面写我该关好狮子 不然他们会吃了我
You're Galileo？No？
你是伽利略？不是？
Okay…
观光客
Hey，I'm the…
我是…
Hi。I'm the new guy and I'm just locking up，so…
我是新来的 我只想关门收工
If it's cool with you I'm just gonna get my paperwork…
如果可以的话 我就看我的书
…and be out of your hair，okay？
不再烦你们 好吗？
「Double-check your belt。The monkey probably stole your keys.」
再检查一次你的腰带 猴子可能偷走钥匙了
Monkey.
猴子
Hey。Hey there。Hi。What's your name？Your name is…
喂 你叫什么名字？
No，no，no。Come back。Come back.
不 回来
Dewey？Is that your name，Dewey？
德伊？那是你的名字吗？
No，no，no。What's…？Dewey？Dexter？Dexter。Dexter，right？
不对 德威？德克斯特
Hey，Dexter，you wanna give me those keys？
德克斯特 把钥匙给我吧？
I just want to lock up.
我只是想锁门
Yes。Oh，good。Come to Papa.
对 很好 过来找爸爸
Oh，thank you。Can I have those keys？Oh，good。What a good boy.
谢谢 能把那些钥匙给我吗？很好 真是个好孩子
That's okay。Oh，thank you.
好 谢谢你
Oh，no，no，no。It's okay。Thank you very，very much.
不 不 没关系 非常 非常感谢你
Bad monkey。Stop that.
坏猴子！快停！
That's not right。Are you done？
那是不对的 你尿完了？
Do you have an issue with me？Do you have an issue with me？
你对我有意见吗？
Because if I have a problem with somebody，I don't pee on them，okay？
因为我就算对人有意见 我也不会乱洒尿
And also… Let me tell you something。These keys？
还有 我告诉你 钥匙在此
Hey。Dexter，that's not funny。Give it back.
德克斯特！这不好玩！快还来！
Dexter。Give…
德克斯特！快还来！
Don't。I know what you're thinking。Don't do it。Not a good idea.
不要 我知道你在想什么 别那么做 那主意不好
Not… Dexter，I need those.
德克斯特 我需要那些纸
Don't encourage him。You think you're funny for your friends，huh？
别鼓励他 你以为你朋友觉得你很有趣？
You three guys… what，he's the ringleader，you're the audience？
怎么 他是头头 你们是观众？
Yeah，no。Don't do it，okay？
别那么做
Lookit… You！
你！
Oh，this is not happening.
这不是真的
Oh，man.
老天
What are you guys doing？
你们干嘛？
I can't feel my lip.
我嘴唇麻了
Oh，shit.
糟糕
Man.
老天
Hey。Hey.
嘿…
Hey，stop that.
住手
Hog-tie him，boys.
把他的腿绑起来
- Get him，that big old Bocephus of a man。- Hey，what are you doing？
- 逮住他这个大猪头 - 你干嘛？
Cinch him up good。You ain't so big now，are you？
把他绑好！这下大也没用了吧
Hey。Hey，stop that.
住手
Every night，year after year…
每晚 年复一年
…one of you guards locks us up in these boxes.
你们其中一个警卫 把我们锁在这些箱子里
Well，I hereby say，sir，enough！
我特此声明 先生…够了！
Fire up the iron horse，boys.
发动火车头
- Hey，blondie？- Name's Jedediah.
- 金发男？- 我叫杰迪戴亚
All right，Jedediah。Stop the train，please.
杰迪戴亚 停住火车
- That's a big no-can-do，cracker Jack。- What's going on here，huh？
- 我无能为力 卧轨男 - 这是怎么回事？
- Somebody's gotta pay。- Pay for what？
- 有人得受到惩罚 - 为什么？
I don't know。Just pay。Now，stop whining and just take it like a man.
我不知道 就是惩罚！别叫了 冷静接受惩罚吧
Seriously，stop the train.
说真的 快停住火车
- All right，stop the train。- Thank you.
- 好吧 停住火车 - 谢谢
Now full speed ahead and ram him！
现在全速前进压烂他
Split his head like a watermelon！
把他的头压个稀巴烂
For crying out loud.
拜托！
All right，that's enough.
真是够了
We got a breach.
有状况！
（巨人逃走了）
I got him。I got him。I got him，guys。I got him…
我逮到他了 我逮到他了 我逮到他了
- oh，my… - Prepare the catapults.
- 老天 - 准备投石器
Octavius，hold on。This ain't your fight。This here giant's on our land.
奥克塔维厄斯 等等 这不是你的战场 这巨人在我们的土地上
Hey，little guy。Jed？Yeah.
小家伙 小杰？
Sorry，look。I just… I'm not a giant。I'm just an average-sized…
我不是巨人 好吗？我身材中等
Don't talk down to me.
别一副高高在上的样子！
I'm not a giant，guys。All right？You guys are really little.
我不是巨人 是你们太小了
We may be small，but our hearts are large…
我们也许小 心却很大
…metaphorically speaking.
这是比喻性的说法
Don't take that wrong。I'm saying you're miniatures.
我只是说你们是很迷你
Silence！The Roman Empire knows no boundaries.
安静！罗马帝国无所不知
- Don't you do it，son。- Do what？
- 别那么做 孩子 - 怎么做？
- Octavius。- Don't do what？
- 奥克塔维厄斯！- 别做什么？
- Unleash hell！- Don't…
- 展开攻击！- 不要
climb aboard，boy.
上来 孩子
Take the hand，son.
握紧我的手 孩子
Onboard.
上马
That's right。You better run，boy。You hear Jedediah？
是啊 快逃吧！听见没？
That mustachioed horseman ain't always gonna be there to protect you，you hear me？
那个八字胡男 他没办法永远保护你的
- Thank you。- Not at all.
- 谢谢你 - 别客气
Theodore Roosevelt，26th president…
西奥多罗斯福 第26任
…of these United States of America at your service.
美国总统 为您效劳
Okay。I'm Larry Daley，the new night guard.
我是拉瑞·戴利 新进夜班警卫
Pleasure to me you，Lawrence Daley。You'll have to excuse me，though.
幸会 拉瑞达理 不过请恕我失礼
The hunt is afoot.
猎杀正在进行
Hunt's afoot.
进行猎杀
Excuse me，Mr。President。Could I ask you something？
总统先生 我能问你一些事吗？
- Yes，but just one question。- All right.
- 可以 不过就一个问题 - 好的
Okay，why？Is it just some，like，three-wishes kind of deal，or…？
为什么？这是阿拉丁神灯吗？
Not at all。Self-reliance is the key to a vigorous life.
不是的 自己才是生存的关键
A man must look inward to find his own answers。How can I be of help？
人要向自己的内心寻求解答 我能帮得上什么忙？
I don't really know how to put this，and please don't take it the wrong way…
我不知该怎么说 请别误会
…but isn't everything in this museum supposed to be，you know…
不过博物馆里的东西 不是应该…
- …dead？- Dead？
- 一片死寂？- 死寂？
- Yeah。- Follow me.
- 对 - 跟我来
Yell all you want，pharaoh.
随你叫吧 法老王
You've been in there 54 years。You're not getting out tonight.
你待54年了 今晚出不去的
There's the source of all this commotion.
那是一切混乱的根源
The Tablet of Ahkmenrah.
阿卡曼拉刻写板
Arrived here in 1952 from the Nile expedition.
1952年尼罗河探险后被送到此
On that night，everything in this museum came to life.
就在当晚 博物馆里的一切都活了过来
And every night since.
之后每晚也都如此
So everything in the museum comes to life every night？
博物馆里的一切每晚都复活？
Exactly.
没错
And I'm supposed to do what？
那我该做些什么？
You're the night watchman，Lawrence。A venerable position in this institution.
你是守夜者 拉瑞 这机构里最值得尊敬的职位
- Come on，lad。- All right。Okay。This is impossible.
- 走吧 - 好了 这是不可能的
Nothing's impossible。If it can be dreamed，it can be done.
没有不可能的事 梦想也能成真
Hence the 20-foot jackal staring at you。Don't make eye contact.
所以巨大的胡狼神瞪着你 别看他
Your job is to make sure that everyone stays inside the museum…
你的工作是确保大家待在博物馆
…because if the sun rises and anyone's on the outside…
当太阳出来 要是有人在外面
…we turn to dust.
我们就会化为尘埃
- You turn to dust？- Dust.
- 尘埃？- 尘埃
- Really？- Really.
- 真的？- 真的
Now，it's almost dawn。I shall help you restore order tonight.
天快亮了 我帮你恢复秩序吧
But mark my words，it's the last time I shall ever do so。Is that clear？
不过这是我最后一次这么做 明白吗？
Yeah。I mean… I mean，I guess。I don't…
明白 我想是吧 我想我不…
Stop babbling，boy！Yes or no？
别唠叨 明白还是不明白？
- Yes。- Good.
- 明白 - 很好
Let's ride.
我们动身吧
All right。So the Hall of Reptiles is secure.
好 爬虫动物厅很安全
What are you looking at？
你在找什么？
I'm tracking，dear boy.
我在…追踪
Man's got to track。Welcome to the family，Lawrence.
有个人必须要追踪 欢迎来到这个大家庭
See you tomorrow night.
明晚见了
Actually，I gotta be honest。I don't think I'm coming back.
说真的 我怀疑我会再来
What？You've only just begun.
什么？你才刚开始呢
Yeah，well，this is not exactly what l…
这不是我想要的
- Lawrence？- Yeah？
- 拉瑞？- 是
What did you do before you took this post？
你之前是做什么的？
Well，I've done a lot of different things。I invented this thing called the Snapper.
很多 我发明过「啪哒弹指器」
Did you give up on that as well？
你也放弃发明了？
No，I just hit a few roadblocks。You might have heard of The clapper？
不 我只是碰上了一些障碍 你听说过「拍掌器」吗？
- Lawrence。- Yes，sir？
- 拉瑞？- 是 先生
Some men are born great。Others have greatness thrust upon them.
有些英雄造时势 有些时势造英雄
For you，this is that very moment.
对你来说 这正是你的时机
Bully。Got you，boy.
妙啊！唬到你了 孩子
Yeah。You got me.
是啊 你是唬到我了
Say hello to your little friend.
跟你的小小朋友打招呼吧
- What are you doing？- Put me down.
- 你干嘛？- 放我下来
I don't like to be manhandled.
我不喜欢被人抓着
- Just calm down，Jed。- It doesn't feel good.
- 冷静点 - 这感觉很不好
- It makes me feel small and powerless。- You done？
- 让我觉得自己渺小又无力 - 说完没？
I'm gonna shoot you in your dang eye。In your dadgum eye.
我要射你的眼睛 射瞎你的狗眼
Yeah，keep shooting。Nothing's gonna happen.
继续射啊 根本不会有事
Now you know my shame.
你现在知道我丢脸的地方了
Jedediah's impotent rage。His guns don't fire。Take me away.
杰迪戴亚无能 他的枪没用
This ain't over。You ain't seen the last of me.
还没完呢 你等着瞧吧
I don't wanna hear it，okay？
我不想听了 好吗？
Duck！
蹲下！
The bigger they are，the harder they fall.
个子越大 摔的越重
This is not worth 11.50 an hour.
这工作给的钟点费也太低了
Look，the giant's scared。There's a bigger giant running around.
巨人好怕 有更大的东西在跑耶
Hello.
喂！
Larry？
拉瑞？
Oh，don't do that。We're too old for surprises.
别那样 我们年纪大不经吓
Really？I thought you liked surprises。Like how you surprised me…
我以为你们喜欢惊喜 像你们给我的惊喜
…with the fact everything in the museum comes to life at night.
像博物馆的东西晚上都会活过来
That little sweetheart.
真是太有趣了
We wanted to tell you。You never would have believed us.
你根本不会相信我们的
- You have any idea what I've been through？- What？
- 你们知道我昨晚怎么过的吗？- 什么？
- You have any idea what I've been through？- Keep a lid on it，butterscotch.
- 你们知道我昨晚怎么过的吗？- 安静点 胆小鬼
I don't know if what happened last night was real，but I didn't sign up for this.
听着 我不知道那是真的假的 但我没同意要参一脚
I just need a regular job that is not life-threatening and pays my bills.
我只是需要一份正常工作 没生命危险 又能应付开销
So thank you very much and I left my uniform in the office…
所以感谢你们 我把制服留在办公室里
- …and I will be seeing you。- Larry！
- 我把制服留在办公室 再见 - 拉瑞！
- Dad？- Hey.
- 爸？- 嘿
Hey，buddy。What are you guys doing here？
小子 你来这干嘛？
Oh，Erica had to be in court early，so I'm taking Mr。Big Stuff here to school.
雅莉要去法院 所以我带大人物先生去学校
But he wanted to swing by，see you in the new job.
他想来看你的新工作
It's so awesome that you're working here.
你在这里工作真棒
Hey，Niko，you wanna take a little look-a-doo inside？
小家伙 要不要进去看看？
Maybe your dad will give you a vlP tour.
也许你爸会给你贵宾级的导览
You know what？We're pretty slammed this morning.
其实 我们今天早上很忙
Yeah，but Nicky，I promise，I'll show you around soon，okay？Deal？
不过尼克 我保证 我很快就带你来参观 好吗？
- Deal。- All right.
- 好 - 很好
- Bye，Dad。- Bye.
- 拜 爸爸 - 拜
- Love you。- Love you too，buddy.
- 我爱你 - 我也爱你 小乖
Bye，now。All right.
再见 好
Hey，Larry.
拉瑞
So I was thinking maybe I'll give it one more night.
我就再试一个晚上吧
I'm glad you came around。Welcome back.
我很高兴 欢迎回来
You。New night guard，here，now.
你！晚班警卫 马上过来
- What's up？- 「What's up？」
- 怎么了？- 「怎么了？」
Oh，well，take a walk with me and I'll show you，Mr.「what's up？」
跟我走 我带你去看 「怎么了先生」
Come on.
来
So would you kindly do me the favor of explaining this？
麻烦你解释这是怎么回事？
Okay。I'm guessing…
好 这个嘛
And I'm just spitballing here，but looks like that Roman dude got cocky…
我也只是猜想啦 不过我想 罗马人太狂妄
…and climbed over into the wild west.
跑进大西部
And the cowboy knows Roman dude wants to take over his territory…
牛仔知道罗马人想夺取他的地盘
…so he rounded up a posse and put him in the stockade.
所以就把他架上示众台
「Let's all laugh at me，the comedy night guard.」
笑吧 搞笑夜班警卫
「No」 is the answer.
答案是不对
Sarcasm back at you，with your humor box.
我这是挖苦你的烂幽默感
I wasn't laughing。Pretending to laugh…
我没笑
…if that's what you want，some sort of battle of humor.
我是假笑 如果那是你想要的 你想比幽默
Do you？
是吗？
No.
不是的
I don't want… No，I don't want a battle of humor.
我并不想比幽默
No，you don't，because it would be a bloodbath.
当然 因为那样你会一败涂地
Nothing funny about Little Bighorn.
大角山战役并不好笑
No。I find it about as funny as a 「fancist.」
我认为那跟追星族一样可笑
It's not funny。Okay？And I will not stand for this type of blatant…
这不好笑 好吗？我不会容许这么过份的…
If I'm not clear，tell me.
要是我没说清楚 告诉我
Am I clear？
我说清楚了吗？
- Yeah。- Yeah？
- 是啊 - 是？
Hey，cecil？
克西？
You got an extra copy of that instruction manual？
那本指令手册你有备份吗？
Oh，no。I'm afraid not，Larry。Listen，I'll tell you what you do.
恐怕没有 我告诉你该怎么做吧
Read some books。Brush up on your history.
去看一些书 重温历史
Helped me a lot when I first started out.
我刚来时 那对我助益很大
This museum was originally dedicated to that man on the horse up there…
这间博物馆是献给那个骑马的人
…President Theodore Roosevelt.
西奥多罗斯福
He absolutely loved history and believed that the more you know about the past…
他喜爱历史 也相信人越明了过去
…the better prepared you are for the future.
就更能准备好迎接未来
Okay，kids。Who can tell me what this room's called？
好了 谁能告诉我这间是什么？
Very good。The Hall of African Mammals.
很好 非洲哺乳动物陈列室
Right here we have the king of the jungle，the lion.
这是丛林之王 狮子
Up ahead is one of my favorite creatures in the whole museum，the capuchin monkey.
上面是我最喜欢的动物之一 僧帽猴
A highly intelligent primate known for its loving and generous nature.
一种具有高度智慧的灵长类 以其仁慈慷慨的天性闻名
Excuse me？
抱歉？
I just thought that was…
我只是觉得…
I just was laughing in agreement.
我只是有同感的笑出来
Happy monkey.
快乐的猴子
All right，kids。This way.
好了 孩子们 往这边来
Let me tell you something。I'm not buying it.
我告诉你 我才不买帐
You might have them fooled，you might have the kids fooled。Not me.
你骗的了小孩 骗不了我 你骗不倒我的
Can't get past me。There's a storm coming，buddy.
等着瞧吧 好戏即将登场
There's a storm coming.
好戏即将登场
One of the most famous trackers in history，Sakagawea was the woman…
历史上最有名的追踪者之一 莎卡佳薇
…who led Lewis and clark on their expedition to find the Pacific ocean.
她引领路易斯和克拉克 找到太平洋
You guys have heard the saying，「Actions speak louder than words.」
你们也许听过这句话 「坐而言不如起而行」
And yet they wrote…
但他们写…
- Yes，Mr。Daley？- Yes。Was she deaf？
- 是的 达理先生？- 她是聋子吗？
Was she deaf？No。She was not。But she…
聋？不 她不是
Yeah，because… Just… She does seem a little bit sort of unresponsive.
因为她看来有点… 没反应
That's because she's a statue.
那是因为她是一尊雕像
Kids，could you give me one sec？Go check her out。She's really cool.
等我一下 去看看她吧 她很酷的
- What are you doing？- I'm gonna be here every night.
- 你这是干嘛？- 既然我每晚都要待在这
I wanted to learn a little bit more about what I'm guarding.
我想认识我所守卫的东西
Actually，I've got a bunch of questions.
事实上 我有一堆问题
Maybe when you have a break，could I buy you a cup of coffee？
等你休息 我能请你喝咖啡吗？
A cup of coffee？
喝咖啡？
Yeah，I mean，just purely a，you know…
对 纯粹是同事对同事
…colleague-to-colleague，information-download sort of coffee.
资讯交流那类的咖啡
I finish in 20 minutes。I'll meet you outside.
过二十分钟再见
- Thank you。- You're welcome.
- 谢谢你 - 不客气
- And have a good rest of your… - All right。Okay，kids.
- 希望你有个好的…- 好了 孩子们
It was incredible what she did.
她很厉害
She literally led these men across rivers，up mountains…
她引领这些人跋山涉水
…all with her newborn baby on her back。She was the ultimate working mother.
她身上还背着孩子 她是终极的职业母亲
Wow，you are quite the Sakagawean expert.
你真是莎卡假薇专家
- Sakagawean。- Sakagawean？
- 是莎卡佳薇 - 莎卡佳薇？
Yeah。I should be，I've been writing my dissertation on her for four years.
这是自然的 我这篇论文准备了四年
You've been working on one paper for four years？That would drive me crazy.
四年写一篇论文？是我铁定会抓狂
Actually，it's more like a 900-page book.
其实那比较像是一本九百页的书
So，what's your story？Have you always wanted to be a security guard？
你呢？你从小就立志当警卫？
- Oh，I didn't mean to… - No，no，no.
- 我不是故意…- 不 不 不
No，I'm divorced and I have a 10-year-old son…
我离婚了 还有个十岁大的儿子
…so I needed to find a more steady situation.
我需要更稳定一点的生活
Got it。So，what can I tell you about the museum？
懂了 你想知道馆里什么事？
Okay，Attila the Hun。What is that guy's problem？
匈奴王阿提拉 他是怎么搞的？
Attila was considered the only genuine threat to the Roman Empire.
他是唯一威胁过罗马帝国的人
「Known as the 'Scourge of God'…
人称「恐怖魔王」
…Attila and his Huns would often tear off the limbs of their helpless victims.
阿提拉和他的手下 常将无助的受害者五马分尸
Attila was famous for his superstitious beliefs.
他以迷信著称
He surrounded himself with a phalanx of sorcerers and magicians…
身旁围绕着巫师和术士
…who advised and mystified him with their dark arts.「
他们以黑魔法迷惑指使他
（复活岛）
（大西部驿马车）
（罗马战争策略）
Larry？
拉瑞？
Just wanted to say good luck，son.
我只想祝你好运
And goodbye。We're clocking out for the last time.
还有再见 这是我们最后一晚
If you're ever in Boca，look us up.
到了波卡 来找我们
Wait，you guys are going out of town？What if this doesn't work out？
你们要出城？万一这一切不顺利呢？
Smart fellow like you？You'll be fine.
你这么聪明 一定没问题的
Yeah。We'll just be a phone call away。Come on，walk us out.
打个电话就能找到我们 送我们出去吧
You fellas go ahead.
你们先走
I need a moment.
我需要独处一下
He's very emotional。A lot of memories in this room.
他很感伤 这房里有许多回忆
Go crazy，big guy.
好好玩吧 大个子
Hey，guys.
你们好
Quest for fire…
找火？
…over。Knock yourselves out.
搞定 自己找乐子吧
Morning，dum-dum.
早安 笨笨
Me no dum-dum。You dum-dum。You bring me gum-gum？
我不笨笨 你笨笨 你有糖糖吗？
Yes，I did，fathead。Lots and lots of gum-gum.
有 大头呆 很多糖糖
What's that？I can't hear you through the glass.
什么？我听不见 玻璃挡住了
Sorry.
抱歉
Heave.
用力拉！
Heave。Heave.
Hey，what's going on over here？
怎么回事？
We expand or we die.
不扩张 就得死
Heave.
用力拉！
- Heave。- On the count of three…
- 用力！- 数到三
…you blow this anthill to kingdom come.
就炸翻这个蚁丘
- And a one and a two… - Hey，Jed。Stop that.
- 一个 两个 - 杰迪戴亚 住手
No，no。You blow a hole in your mountain，all you're gonna hit is a wall.
别这样 你炸山 只是在炸墙
Step aside，Gigantor。We got us a railroad to build。We're blowing a hole in that thing.
别管闲事 巨怪 我们要建铁道 要炸山洞
Okay，first of all，enough with the Gigantor giant stuff，okay？
第一 别再叫我什么巨怪了
- I'm just trying to close up shop。- We're gonna blow it anyway。And a three！
- 我只想停止这一切 - 我们就是要炸
Yeah。What are you doing？
是啊 碰 了不起 你干嘛？
What's it look like we're doing？It's manifest destiny.
这像干嘛？这是天命
You can't fight it and neither can I。Go！More dynamite.
你无法与之抗衡 我也一样 再多用点火药
- Yeah，use it all。- All right。Okay.
- 对 全用了 - 好啊 很好
Listen，「octavus」？You gotta stop that.
听着 屋大尾？你得停止那样
It's octavius，mary.
我叫奥克塔维厄斯 赖皮
Okay，you know what？Fine。Great。Here you go。This is what happens.
好吧 来 事情就会变成这样
- You cannot do this。I am a Roman general。- Sorry.
- 你不能这样 我是罗马将军 - 抱歉
- I have rights。- And you.
- 我有权利 - 还有你
- Hey，no！Put me down！- Keep heaving，men.
- 嘿 不 放我下来 - 继续攻
You can't stop progress！
我会回来的 我发誓
We're gonna have a little talk，okay？
我们要谈一谈
I told you，I don't like to be manhandled.
我说过我不喜欢被人抓着
No，I will manhandle you，Jedediah。Now，listen，guys.
不 我要抓着你
What is your problem，huh？Why can't you just get along？
你们到底是怎样？为什么老处不来？
Look，we're men。We fight，okay？That's what we do.
我们是男人 我们战斗 就这样
It's kind of how we pass the time.
我们都这样杀时间
You're，like，a giant。A freak，if you will。We can't expect you to understand that.
你是巨人 怪胎 你没办法了解的
You got the whole room to run around in。You don't have to be near each other.
空间很大 你们不用腻在一起
- What，you mean…？- You're gonna let us out？
- 什么？你是说 - 你要让我们出去？
What，and just roam free？
四处闲逛？
Yeah。Yeah，I might，if you promise to behave.
有可能 只要你们保证不乱来
That means no fireballs，no explosions，okay？
那表示没火花 没爆炸
You have my word，my liege.
我敢起誓 主人
Yeah，no problemo，Gigantor.
是啊 没问题 巨怪
My name's Larry，first of all。Okay，Jed？
首先 我的名字叫拉瑞 阿嘉
So I call you Jed。I don't call you Tiny，right？
我叫你阿嘉 不叫你小人
What's that supposed to mean？
那是什么意思？
- 「Hey，Teeny.」 How does that sound？- I don't like it。It hurts my feelings.
- 小鬼头 如何？- 我不喜欢 我很受伤
「Gigantor」 makes me feel like some sort of freak，so…
「巨怪」也让我觉得像怪胎
I don't。I just call you Larry.
我不会那样 我就叫你拉瑞
Don't be a kiss-ass，okay？
少谄媚了
Look，I'm trusting you guys，all right？
我现在信任你们
If you don't do what I say，you can end up like the Mayan world there.
你们要是不听我的话 就会跟小马雅人一样
Locked up。Take a look.
被关起来 你们看
- Do they look happy？- No.
- 他们看来高兴吗？- 不
They look sad.
他们看来很难过
They can't do what they wanna do。Now，I'm letting you guys…
因为他们不能为所欲为
…have a little bit of leash here。Don't choke me with it，okay？
现在我给你们一点自由 别让我失望
I gotta run。You guys play nice，okay？Okay。Good。Thanks.
我得走了 好好相处 好吗？好 谢了
Hey，how's that gum treating you，dum-dum？
笨笨 糖糖好吃吗？
Good.
好吃
Oh，hey，Dexter。I'm just locking up。You want in？
德克斯特 我要锁了 要进来吗？
Yeah？
很好
All right.
好吧
What's that？You got my keys？
什么？你拿了我的钥匙？
I don't think so.
我可不这么想
Looks like Uncle Larry pulled a fast one on little Dexie.
看来老拉瑞骗过小德克斯特了
Those are baby keys for a little baby.
那是给小宝宝玩的玩具钥匙
Have fun with your baby keys，little baby monkey.
好好玩吧 小猴子
Tomorrow I'll bring you a little baby diapy so you can go poo-poo in it.
也许明天我会带纸尿布给你 你可以拿来便便
I'll give you a tickle because you're a cute baby.
我会搔搔你的痒 因为你是可爱的小猴子
While you cry all night long about how Uncle Larry fooled you，huh？
拉瑞叔叔骗你 你要哭整晚吗？
I told you there was a storm coming.
我说过好戏即将登场
- Hey，Teddy。- Lawrence.
- 你好 泰迪 - 拉瑞
You impertinent pup。I knew you'd come back.
你这个没礼貌的小子 我就知道你会回来
- You look like a man on a mission。- Yeah，I'm gonna give it another shot.
- 你看来身负重任 - 我准备再试一次
- You…？- What？
- 你 - 什么…
- You checking her out？- The nerve.
- 你在打量她？- 真敢说
Checking her out。I've never heard of such a thing.
打量 我没听过这种说法
No，no，no。I'm just… I mean because，you know，she's very beautiful.
不 我是说 她很美
- Beautiful？- Yeah.
- 美？- 是啊
- Rather handsome woman，I suppose。- Yeah.
- 我认为是个俊俏的女人 - 是啊
I don't know，maybe you should go talk to her.
也许你该去跟她说个话
- Indeed。Bless you，lad。- Yeah。All right.
- 是啊！- 祝福你 小子
- Carry on。- Good。See you.
- 继续加油吧 - 好 再见
I…
我…
Hey，hi.
嘿 嗨
No！It's okay！It's okay。You guys speak English？
不 没关系 没关系 你们会说英文吗？
No？
不会？
Right。I don't know what that means…
是啊 我不知道那是什么意思
…and I know that you and I got off on the wrong foot last night，but…
不过我知道我们一开始就没搞好 但是…
…a little birdie told me that somebody likes…
有只小鸟告诉我 有人喜欢
…magic.
魔法
- Magic？- Magic.
- 魔法？- 魔法
Sorcery.
巫术
Ah，sorcer…
Yes。Illusion.
对 幻术
Everybody likes magic.
大家都喜欢魔法
And flowers。People like flowers.
还有花 人们都喜欢花
There you go。Those are for you.
那些是给你的
You know what else people like？Money.
人们还喜欢什么？钱
The almighty dollar，right？But money can sometimes…
无所不能的金钱 但金钱有时候会…
…disappear.
不见
At least that's what I…
至少我是这么…
…hear.
听说的
No wonder you can't understand me。You got a coin in your ear.
难怪你不懂我的话 你耳里有钱
Check this out。Anybody need a hanky？
你们看 有人需要手帕吗？
Well，I wouldn't suggest this little feller because he has a nasty habit…
我不建议拿这条小手帕 因为这顽皮的家伙
…of vanishing…
会凭空
…into thin air！
消失
No，no。Don't。That defeats the… Don't！
不要 那会穿帮…
Not the limbs。Guys，please，do not tear the limbs.
别五马分尸 各位 拜托 别五马分尸
Cortes，right？
蔻蒂兹 对吧？
How？
怎么会？
You！Don't even think about it。Don't you…
想都别想
Dexter！
德克斯特
Come on，guys！
拜托你们
Hey，guys！
喂 你们
Hey，guys。Hey，guys！
嘿 两位…
Sorry。What's going on？What happened here？
抱歉 怎么回事？
I thought we had a deal.
你们在干嘛？我们不是讲好了？
We will never coexist with these buffoons.
我们永远无法忍受这些小丑
We're past words，Laredo.
承诺已成过去 小赖
Now it's time to let Smith & wesson do the talking！
该让手上的家伙说话了
Those guns don't even work.
那玩意根本没用
They don't？Take a look at this.
是吗？你看着
Dexter！
德克斯特！
Why？
为什么？
Ho！Dexter.
德克斯特
End of the line，cool breeze.
你无路可逃了 小毛猴
End of the line.
无路可逃
I am not playing games here.
我可不是闹着玩的
Just hand them over.
快给我
Easy。That's it，Dexter.
小心 很好 德克斯特
Nice and easy，Dex。That's it.
慢慢来 就是这样
Good Lord，Lawrence！Why are you slapping a monkey？
老天 你干嘛打猴子？
Teddy，this guy's been pushing me，and I'm sick of it！
这家伙一直惹我 我受够了
Poppycock。This little creature is your primate brother.
胡说 这小家伙是你的远亲
Without him，there's no us.
没有他 就没有我们
Are you rabid？
你得了狂犬病啦？
Wipe that off.
把泡泡擦干净
You have to deal with this creature with love and respect.
你得对这小家伙展现爱和尊重
May I have the keys，dear friend？
朋友 可以把钥匙给我吗？
Thank you。Lawrence？
谢谢 拉瑞？
Well，you know what？
知道么
You seem to know what you're doing，so I'm gonna let you take over.
你似乎很清楚该怎么做 所以我就让你接手
No，no。My dear boy，you can't put up the white flag now.
你不能现在就举白旗
The museum is on the verge of total anarchy.
博物馆正濒临无政府状态
I tried！I came back tonight，didn't I？
我试过了 我今晚回来了
Tried？That was one night。I didn't build the Panama canal in one day.
就一晚 我也建不好巴拿马运河
That's great，but I'm dealing with the most ridiculous job in history.
很好 但这是史上最荒谬的工作
Some men are born great，Lawrence…
有些英雄造时势
Yeah，I know。Others have greatness thrust upon them.
是 我知道 泰迪 有些时势造英雄
You hit me with that chestnut last night.
你昨晚就说过那句话了
The thing is，not everyone is great.
不过不是每个人都是英雄
That's the problem。Some of us are just ordinary.
有些人只是普通人
No，you're not，Lawrence。Stop wallowing in self-pity.
你不是 别再顾影自怜了
Every journey begins with a footstep.
每个伟大的旅程 都是由第一步开始
Teach the inhabitants to get along，they wouldn't need to be locked up.
要是你能教导居民和平相处 他们就不用被关起来了
That means a lot coming from a guy who's spent the last 50 years…
夜复一夜的 这话出自花五十年偷看女人
…spying on a girl he's never even talked to.
却不敢开口的人口中 还真有用
I was going to make contact。Lawrence，please.
我本来要去跟她说话的 拜托
I'm done，all right？
我受够了 好吗？
No，Rexy！No！
不 笨龙
Oh，no.
不！
All right.
好吧
No one comes here anymore。Besides，I took this tour in second grade，Daley.
没人会再来这了 何况我二年级就来过了
I'm telling you，my dad's gonna hook us up.
我爸会给我们私人导览的
- Mr。Daley？- Yeah？
- 达理先生？- 是
- Foam。- Yes，I know.
- 泡沫 - 是啊 我知道
In the Neanderthal display.
在尼安德塔人展示区里！
There was an incident last night with the fire extinguisher.
昨天晚上 灭火器出了点状况
I was on my way to go clean it up.
我正要去清理
Okay，don't bother。You're fired.
不用麻烦 你被炒了
I don't think we're getting a tour today.
今天没得参观了
Your dad just got canned，dude.
你爸刚被炒了
Excuse me？
抱歉
Mr。McPhee？
麦菲先生？
Excuse me，Mr。McPhee？
抱歉 麦菲先生？
Can I talk to you about this，please？
我能跟你谈一谈吗？
- Sir？- What？
- 先生？- 干嘛？
I know I screwed up，but I finally understand how to do this job.
我错了 但我现在知道该怎么做了
- You obviously don't。- No，I didn't，but now I do.
- 你显然是不知道 - 我本来不知 但现在知道了
- Really，Mr。McPhee… - Doctor.
- 真的 麦菲先生 - 博士
Dr。McPhee.
麦菲博士
Can you please give me one more night？
你能再给我一个晚上吗？
- One more night。- Okay，thank you.
- 就再一晚 - 好 谢谢
And if anything is the tiniest…
要是你当班之后
…after your shift：
有任何事发生
Because…
因为…
- Got it。- Okay？
- 我明白 - 好吗？
Fool me once，shame on you。Fool me twice…
骗我一次 是我丢脸 骗我两次
Shame on me。Fool me… Shame on me.
是我丢脸…我丢脸
- You。- Fool me twice… Got it.
- 你 - 骗我两次 我明白
- Take it or leave it。- Okay。Thank you.
- 接不接受随你 - 好 谢谢
- Hey。- Hey.
- 嘿 - 嘿
- What's wrong？- Maybe you should ask Nicky.
- 怎么了？- 也许你该去问尼克
Hey，buddy。What's going on？
小子 怎么回事？
You got fired.
你被炒了
What are you talking about？I didn't get fired.
什么？我并没有被炒啊
I came to the museum this morning。I saw your boss yelling at you.
我今早去了博物馆 你老板对你大吼
Why didn't you tell me？Everything's fine.
你怎么没告诉我？一切都没事
We just had a little misunderstanding.
没事 我们只是有点误会
Why？
为什么？
It's hard to explain。I mean，you wouldn't bel…
很难解释 我是说 你不会相信…
You know what？Let me show you.
这样吧 我就让你见识一下
- Show me what？- Come to work with me tonight.
- 见识什么？- 跟我一起去上班
Larry？
拉瑞？
Can I talk to you for a second？
我能跟你谈一谈吗？
Am I in trouble？
我有麻烦吗？
Larry，what are you doing？
拉瑞 你在干嘛？
I just wanna show him what I do。That's all.
我想让他看看我的工作
I love that you wanna share that with him，but I gotta tell you…
我很高兴你想和他分享 可是
…I don't think Nicky has any room in his heart for more disappointment.
我不认为尼克能再次承受失望
He won't be disappointed.
他不会失望的
Larry.
拉瑞
He won't be disappointed.
他不会失望的
Listen，hang out in the security office till everyone's gone.
在警卫室等到大家离开
- Then I'm gonna come get you。All right？- Okey.
- 之后我就会来找你 好吗？- 好
Hey，miss？I'm gonna have to ask you to vacate the premises.
小姐？我得请你离开本馆
- Hey there。- Hey.
- 你好 - 嘿
- Good place to think，huh？- Yeah。Definitely.
- 很棒的沉思之地 - 是啊
So no big plans tonight？
今晚没约会啊？
Yeah，no，I'm not really a big-plan person.
我不大喜欢约会
I prefer hanging out with people who are dead for 200 years.
我喜欢跟已死之人相处
It's the live ones that throw me.
活人令我困惑
That's cool。Seriously though，you do have to leave.
但说真的 你得走了
- Seriously？- Yeah，sorry。It's museum rules.
- 认真的？- 抱歉 博物馆的规定
We're sort of locking everything up.
我们要把一切都锁起来
You're really taking your job seriously.
你很认真执行你的工作
You know，once I clip on the tie，I'm all business.
我一戴上领带 就很认真
- I get it。- Yeah.
- 我明白了 - 好
How's that dissertation coming？
论文进度如何？
I've hit a dead end。I mean，research can only get me so far.
我遇上瓶颈了 研究只能让我到此为止
I'm never gonna know who she really was.
我永远不会认识真正的她
So I think it's time that I move on to another subject.
我想我该研究别的主题了
I'll let you get back to work.
我就让你继续工作吧
- Good night，Larry。- Yeah，okay.
- 晚安 拉瑞 - 好…
Night.
晚安
Hey.
嘿
Rebecca！
贝嘉
- Hey，Rebecca。- Hey.
- 嘿 贝嘉 - 嘿
Hey。Listen，I don't think you should give up on your paper.
我不认为你该放弃你的论文
Okay。Why？
好吧 为什么？
All right，look，this is gonna sound crazy，all right？
这听起来可能有点疯狂
I mean，it's gonna sound，like，really，really crazy.
听起来真的很疯狂
- Okay。- No，I mean insanely crazy.
- 好吧 - 我是说超疯狂的疯狂
- I can handle it。- Okay.
- 我能接受 - 好
You know how they say in certain museums，history comes alive？
你知道在某些博物馆里 历史会栩栩如生
- Yeah。- In this museum…
- 是啊 - 在这间博物馆里
…it actually does.
一切真的活了过来
What are you talking about？
你在胡说什么？
Everything in this museum comes to life at night.
这馆内的一切在晚上都会活过来
- Really？- Yeah，really。I'm not kidding you.
- 真的？- 是真的 我没骗你
You know that tablet？The Tablet of Ahkmenrah？
你知道阿卡曼拉刻写板吧？
It actually brings things to life。It's like some ancient spell.
它让一切活过来
Since the '50s，every night everything's been coming to life.
自它来了以后 一切都活了过来
Teddy Roosevelt told me。Seriously。The monkey，Dexter？The cute little…
泰迪罗斯福跟我说的 真的！那只猴子 德克斯特？
- what is he？- Capuchin.
- 他是什么来着？- 僧帽猴
A capuchin。Right。The capuchin。He urinated on me and bit my nose.
僧帽猴 他咬了我的鼻子 还在我身上撒了尿
And Sakagawea is in her case，alive every night…
莎卡佳薇在柜子里 每晚都复活
…just listening to Lewis and clark argue.
聆听路易斯和克拉克吵嘴
So if you really wanna get inside her head…
所以你要是想了解她
…I can hook that up.
我能帮你安排
That's cool.
真是太棒了
Yeah，it's cool。It's freaking awesome.
是啊 是很棒 棒呆了
Make fun of the history geek.
嘲笑历史学者
- No。Rebecca！- Good night，Larry.
- 不是的 贝嘉 - 晚安 拉瑞
No，I'm not making fun of you。Rebecca.
我不是在嘲笑你 贝嘉？
- Here you go。Best seat in the house。- What's going on？
- 馆内的最佳座位 - 怎么回事？
If I told you，you'd think I'm crazy。I'm gonna show you.
用说的你不会信 我让你自己看
- What？- You'll see in about 20 seconds.
- 什么？- 你再过20秒就会看到了
- Okay，you like Tyrannosaurus Rex？- Yeah.
- 你喜欢暴龙吧？- 喜欢
Yeah？Well，I call him Rexy.
我叫他小龙
And he's about to come to life，Nicholas，in…
他就快活过来了 儿子 再过
…five，four，three，two…
五 四 三 二
- Dad？- Hang on a sec.
- 爸？- 等一下
Say hello to Rexy！
跟小龙打声招呼吧
Dad，are you okay？
爸 你没事吧？
This is weird.
怪了
Guys！Come on！
大家出来啊！
Sundown！
太阳下山了
Hey，T.R.，come on，rise and shine。Buddy，I need you to wake up.
总统 起床了 我要你醒来
Come on，my kid is here。I need you to wake up.
我儿子来了 醒醒啊
Texas？Texas！Come on！Texas！Come on！Get on，Texas！
德克萨斯？快点 快跑啊
Get on，Texas！Get up.
快跑 德克萨斯
Just stop，okay？
别闹了 好吗？
No，Nicky，I'm telling you，there's this tablet，okay？
尼克 我告诉你 那里有个板子
Called the Tablet of Ahkmenrah。Every night…
阿卡曼拉刻写板
- Now there's a tablet？- Yeah，there is.
- 这下又有个板子了？- 是啊
Come on，Dad.
拜托 爸
Come on.
跟我来
- It's gone。- What's gone？
- 它不见了 - 什么不见了？
The tablet。I think somebody stole it.
板子 我想有人偷走了它
Yeah，right.
是啊
I'm not kidding，Nicky.
我不是开玩笑的 儿子
Nicky？
尼克？
Hey，Nicky！
嘿 尼克
Hey！Hey，Nicky！Where are you going？
嘿 尼克 你要去哪？
- Home。- What？Wait a minute.
- 回家 - 等一下
Come on.
走吧
You guys shouldn't be here.
你们不该在这里的
Give us the tablet，son.
把板子给我们
Wait a minute，Nicky。What are you guys doing？
等等 尼克 你们在干嘛？
We're not gonna hurt you。Give us the tablet.
我们不会伤害你 把板子给我们
I'm sorry to tell you this，son，but your dad doesn't work here.
抱歉告诉你这一切 孩子 不过你爸不在这工作
He got fired this morning。Couldn't hack it.
他被炒了 无法胜任
Dad？I thought you said you weren't fired.
爸？你说过你没被炒的
I did。They're lying，trying to steal that thing.
他们骗人 这样他们才能偷东西
Turn the middle piece，you'll see what I was talking about.
把中间那块翻过来 你就明白了
That is museum property，son。Give it back.
那是博物馆的财产 孩子 拿给我
Nicky，trust me。Just turn it.
尼克 相信我 快翻
- Give us the tablet！- Nicky？
- 把板子给我们 - 尼克？
Trust me.
相信我
Nick？Run。Now.
尼克？快跑
Get back here，kid！
给我回来 小鬼
Bad idea，Larry.
坏主意 拉瑞
You wanna dance，hot dog？You wanna dance？
想打架吗？
Gus，you're an old man。I don't wanna hurt you.
葛斯 你是老人 我不想伤你
You see，Larry，a few years into the job，the three of us realized that…
拉瑞 担任这工作几年下来 我们就明白
…like everything else in this museum，we got new life at night.
我们就像博物馆里的一切 夜里会有新生命
Sundown to sunrise，we felt young again.
日落到日出 我们都重获新生
Okay。Did not see that coming.
我没想到有那招
Gave us an energy boost.
让我们重获活力
We love the nightlife，Larry.
我们喜欢夜生活 拉瑞
So when we found out they were gonna fired us…
所以一等他们辞退我们
…we had to steal the tablet.
我们就得偷走板子
Everyone knows you need the money.
大家都知道你需要钱
Add the stuff we planted in your place…
栽赃在你家的赃物
…pretty obvious you committed the crime.
刚好成了你的罪证
Take care of that cut.
好好照料伤口
Come on，guys，let's go find that kid.
我们去找那个小鬼吧
- Sweet dreams，cupcake！- No！
- 祝你好梦 呆头 - 不！
Pile driver！
岩石落下技！
Let's get our tablet.
我们去拿板子吧
Thank you very much。We'll take it from here.
谢谢 我们就从这里接手
Nicky！
尼克
Just in time，Larry。We were just locking up.
刚好 我们正要锁门呢
Sleep tight，hotshot.
好好睡吧
Let's grab everything we can fence.
快去拿值钱的东西吧
I don't know about you，but I'm planning on a long retirement.
我打算要过一段好日子
Teddy！Teddy，if you're out there，I need you，pal！
泰迪！你在的话 我需要你
Someone call my name？
有人叫我吗？
Theodore Roosevelt，at your service.
西奥多罗斯福 为您效命
Teddy，can you get us out of here？
泰迪 你能带我们出去吗？
Can't do it，man。This is your moment.
做不到 这是你人生的机会
Will you save the lectures，please？I'm not you。Okay？
拜托你少开讲了 我不是你
I didn't build the Panama canal，I wasn't president of the United States！
我没建巴拿马运河 也不是总统
I need some help。Come on.
我需要帮忙
Actually…
事实上
…I never did any of those things。Teddy Roosevelt did.
那些事也不是我做的 是泰迪罗斯福做的
I was made in a mannequin factory in Poughkeepsie.
我是模型工厂的产品
I never shot a wild beast.
我从未射杀过野兽
I'm not even brave enough to tell that beautiful woman I love her.
我也没勇气告诉那位女士我爱她
But you…
不过你
…you gotta finish the job this time。You can't quit.
你这次得完成这个工作 你不能放弃
I'm made of wax，Larry.
我是蜡做的 拉瑞
What are you made of？
你又是什么做的？
- Wait！That's all you got for me？- That's it！
- 等等 那就是你的忠告？- 没错
That's it。Come on.
这就对了 来吧
Duck！
低头！
Go over there！
过去
Hey。Hi。How you doing？Sorry to bother you…
嗨 你好吗？抱歉打扰你了
…but your guys there？Your jackal guys？
不过 你的卫兵 你的胡狼神…
Do you think you could ask them to back off，please？
你能不能请他们退下？
We're not trying to hurt you，they think we are。Could you do it like now？
我们不想伤你 但他们不这么想 拜托你快点！
Thank you。Nicky.
谢谢你 尼克
Thank you.
谢了
Dad？
爸？
You would not believe how stuffy it is in there.
你不会相信这里面有多闷
- How come you speak English？- I went to cambridge University.
- 你怎么会说英文？- 我上过剑桥
You went to cambridge？
你上过剑桥？
I was on display in the Egyptology Department.
我在埃及古物学系作过展示
I am Ahkmenrah，fourth king of the fourth king…
我是阿卡曼拉 第四王朝的第四任国王
…ruler of the land of my fathers.
我父亲王国的统治者
I am Larry…
我是拉瑞
…son of Milton…
密尔顿之子
…and this is my son，Nick.
这是我儿 尼克
And we hail from Brooklyn.
我们来自布鲁克林
Well，I do。I mean，he comes out and stays with me on wednesdays…
就我啦 他每周三和…
…and every other weekend.
隔周周末跟我住
That was the custody agreement that we had.
监护权的协议
Larry，Nick，guardians of Brooklyn…
拉瑞 尼克 布鲁克林守护者
…I am forever in your debt.
我永远感谢你们
Now bestow the tablet upon me…
现在请将刻写板给我
…so that I may assume command of my kingdom.
好让我重掌我的王国
Oh，yes。Okay，the tablet。I would…
好 刻写板 我很乐意
…love to bestow it upon you，but we don't actually…
将它返回给你 可是它不在
…have it.
我们手上
Thanks，guys。Don't worry。I'll watch out for him！
谢了 我会保护他的
Thank you.
谢谢
What is that？
那是什么？
Huns.
匈奴人
I gotta deal with this guy.
我得解决这个家伙
Pardon me，Larry。I speak Hun.
抱歉 拉瑞 我会说匈奴话
He says that he wants to rip you apart.
他想把你五马分尸
All right。Again with the ripping。Listen，I understand.
又要分尸 我明白
I get it。Ripping for you… You want to rip things，okay？
我懂了 你想撕扯什么
And I think maybe that's because somebody ripped you a long time ago.
也许是因为很久以前 有人撕扯了你
In here.
在这里
Somebody ripped little…
很久以前
…baby Attila a long time ago，right here.
有人伤了小阿提拉 就在这里
They ripped something out，didn't they？
他们摧毁了某个东西 对吧？
They ripped the love.
他们摧毁了爱
They ripped the love right out of you，didn't they？
让你失去了爱
A little baby all alone in a tent…
小宝宝孤单待在帐棚里
…whose daddy went off…
爸爸出门去
…to pillage some town…
去掠夺某个城镇 或者
…or go and plunder somewhere，just doing his job.
去抢某个地方 做他该做的事
But who was left alone？
可是谁被扔在家里？
You.
你
Let it out。Let it go。Let it go.
别压抑 释放出来吧
It's okay。It's okay.
没事了 没事了
You're next.
你是下一个
Good。That's good。Just breathe.
很好 深呼吸
- Larry Daley。- Yeah.
- 拉瑞·戴利 - 在
Good。Yes.
很好
Yeah。Okay。Good，good.
是 很好 很好
All right！I need everybody to listen up！
好了 大家听着
Guys！Come on！
各位 听我说
Quiet！
安静！
My dum-dum want to speak.
我的笨笨有话要说
Thank you.
谢谢
Now，this here's King Ahkmenrah.
这位是阿卡曼拉王
His tablet is what brings you to life every night.
他的板子让各位每晚重获新生
And those old night watchmen？They stole it.
这些夜班老警卫偷走了它
Now，we need to find those guards and get the tablet back…
在天亮之前
…and we need to do it before morning.
我们得找到这些警卫 拿回板子
Civil war guys，head over to the Planetarium wing.
南北战争士兵！快去天文馆
My explorer friend whose name escapes me.
我不记得我探险家朋友的名字了
- It's columbus。- Right，columbus！Right，I'm sorry.
- 是哥伦布 - 哥伦布！对 真抱歉
There's no nameplate，so… columbus，take the Neanderthals…
你又没挂名牌 哥伦布 带尼安德塔人去搜索
…and do a sweep from Invertebrates all the way through Reptiles.
无脊椎和爬虫类动物陈列室
Jed and octavius，their van's parked out back。Go take care of it.
杰迪戴亚和奥克塔维厄斯 他们的货车在后面 看住它
Whoa，whoa，whoa，no！No，sir。I ain't working with toga boy.
不要 我不跟穿袍子的人合作
Romans work alone.
罗马人单打独斗
- That didn't hurt。Don't be a baby。- Yes，it did.
- 那又不会痛 少孩子气了 - 会痛啦！
Come on.
少蠢了
That was much harder！
那一下比较用力
Guys，come on！
两位 拜托
Jed，octavius.
阿嘉 奥克塔维厄斯
Take away the fact you were born 2000 years apart…
你们的年代虽然差了两千年
…you guys aren't that different.
但你们并没有那么大的差异
You're both great leaders.
你们都是伟大的领袖
You just want what's best for your people，right？
你们都为自己的人民谋福利 对吗？
- Yeah。- Yeah.
- 对 - 对
Civil war dudes.
南北战争的兵士们
You guys are brothers，for God's sakes。You gotta stop fighting.
拜托 你们是同胞 别再打斗了
North wins。Slavery's bad。Sorry.
北方赢了 奴隶不对 抱歉
Don't wanna burst your bubble。But，South，you guys get Allman Brothers…
我并不想毁了你们的幻想 不过南方 你们有艾曼兄弟
…and NAScAR，so just chill！
还有房车赛 别激动了
Look，without that tablet，all of this…
听着 没有了刻写板 这一切
…this whole coming-to-life-at-night thing，it all goes away.
夜生活就会划下休止符
Now，I don't wanna let that happen，but I need your help.
我不想那样 但我需要你们帮忙
We can get this done，but we gotta do it together.
我们做得到 但我们得齐心合力
So who's with me？
谁要帮我？
Yeah.
好
- Who's with me？- Yeah！
- 谁跟我同一阵线？- 好耶！
- Yeah！- Charge！
- 好啊 - 冲啊！
All right！Now，let's do this，people！
好耶 我们动手吧
And animals！
还有动物们
And weird，faceless puppet creatures。Come on，let's go！Let's do it！
还有无脸男们 一起来吧
Come on！Follow me，boys！
跟我来 各位
Geronimo！
吉拉尼莫！
Oh，jeez.
天哪
Now，boys，we can do this the easy way or the hard way.
各位 要来软的还是硬的
I guess it's gonna be the hard way.
我想你们是想来硬的
Right，men，we're almost there.
我们就快到了
Save yourself！
救救你自己吧
I ain't quitting you！
我不想戒掉你
Gus？
葛斯？
Reginald？
雷纳？
Fellas，where are you？
两位？你们在哪里？
Guys？
兄弟们？
That's what I'm talking about。Good job，gentlemen.
我就说嘛 干的好！
Loving the teamwork！
团队合作太棒了
They've vanished。How will we find them？
他们消失了 要怎么找他们？
I know someone who can help。Come on.
我知道有人能帮忙 来吧
Watch out！
小心！
Hey，Sakagawea，or wea。Listen，I need a favor。Somebody stole his tablet.
莎卡佳尾 或佳薇 有人偷了他的板子
You think you can track the guys who took it？
你能追踪拿走它的人吗？
He went east but he lost control and crashed.
他往东走 不过失控撞车了
You're amazing。How can you tell that？
真厉害 你怎么知道的？
He left the wagon…
他放弃车子
…and went back.
跑回去了
He went back？
跑回去？
Why would he go back？
他为什么要回去？
Get out of the way！
让开！
You saved me.
你救了我
You're worth saving，my dear.
你值得我救 亲爱的
- That's problematic。- Teddy。Oh，man.
- 这下有问题了 - 泰迪 老天
Larry，relax。I'm wax.
拉瑞 别紧张 我是蜡做的
You gotta do something。Dawn's approaching.
不过快天亮了
- Half the museum's running amuck outside。- He's got my tablet.
- 馆里大半的东西都在外面乱跑 - 他拿了我的板子
Come on，ockie！
走吧 小屋
At your service，Gigantor！
为您效劳 巨怪
How can we be of assistance，my liege？
主人 我们该怎么帮忙？
Just give me a second，guys.
让我想一下
Rexy？
小龙？
Here，boy.
过来 小乖
Teddy，I need a horse.
泰迪 我需要一匹马
Do it，man.
快去吧
- Come on，boy！Let me hear you yell！- Yeah！
- 来啊 让我听你吼吧！- 嗯
Just living the dream，baby！
这真是梦想成真
I'm loving this！
我爱死这一切了
Pull the stagecoach over now！
快停住马车 现在！
Can I make this turn up here？
这个弯能交给我吗？
I'll take that as a yes。Hang on！
我就当是答应了 坐稳了
I can't hold it！
我控制不了它
Come on，Tex，let's finish this.
走 我们了结这一切吧
Come on！
快啊
Give me the tablet，cecil！
把板子给我
Can't do it，son.
做不到
Pull over！
停下
It ain't gonna happen。Moving on.
那是不可能的 走吧
Last chance，cecil。Stop the horses or I will！
快停住 不然我就动手了
They can't be stopped，Larry.
他们停不住的
Don't you know your history？
你历史没学好吗？
These are money carriers。They were trained not to stop for anything but a secret word.
他们是载运钱财的 他们只听一个秘密指令
Really？You mean a word like…
真的吗？你是说像…
…「Dakota」？
达科塔！
Come on，Tex.
过去 德克萨斯
I read up on my history。Thanks for the tip.
我温习过历史了 感谢指点
Oh，and by the way…
还有
…don't ever talk to me like that in front of my son.
别在我儿子面前那样对我说话我
Moving on.
走吧
- Hey，Huns。- Tell Attila to have his boys…
- 嘿 匈奴人 - 叫阿提拉让他的手下
…take him back。Put him with the guards.
把他跟其他警卫绑在一起
Oh，and no limb ripping，okay？
还有 别五马分尸了
Hey，boy。Wait，wait，hold the phone.
等等 别急 不要那么激动
What's makeekaka mean？Wait。Translation，please.
「马基卡卡」啥意思？翻译一下 拜托
The year was 1909。I was going up the Zambezi River in Africa.
那是在1909年 我沿尚比西河而上
And our river guide was a brilliant Pygmy who spoke only by clicking.
我们的矮黑人向导用喀嗒声说话
There we are.
好了
- Oh，boy。- What is it？
- 老天 - 怎么了？
I gotta get you guys back to the museum.
我得把你们弄回博物馆
How？
怎么弄？
Ahkmenrah，I'm gonna need your help.
阿卡曼拉 我需要你帮忙
This is your tablet。You know the instructions。You get everyone back.
你懂板上的文字 你送大家回去
Come on。There's somebody who's gotta see this.
有个人得看看这个
What I'm saying is，for the type of money that they pay A-Rod…
他们每季付A-Rod这么多钱
…he ought to be bringing home a world Series trophy every season.
他每季都该打赢世界大赛
You know what I mean？
你懂我的意思吧？
Now，who they gonna get to clean up all that doo-doo？
谁来帮它们清大便啊？
- Inuit。- Yeah.
- 伊努特人 - 在
One terracotta soldier.
一个陶土士兵
- Vikings。- Right.
- 维京海盗 - 在
- Alpaca。- Welcome back，ladies.
- 羊鸵 - 欢迎回来 女士们
- Llama。- Hey.
- 骆马 - 嘿
Viking guys.
维京海盗
Do me a favor。Your fellows made some funeral pyre…
你们在化石森林古迹
…in Petrified wood。Go clean that up.
搞了个火葬之类的东西 去清干净
Okay？Thank you.
好吗？谢谢
- He's back。- All right，I'll deal with this joker.
- 他回来了 - 我来处理这烦人的家伙
Hey，hey，Moose。It's not gonna happen，buddy。All right？
大糜鹿 你过不来的
I told you，you can't come through with those antlers.
你头上的角会卡住
So you and your caribou buddy gotta go around to the loading dock.
带着你的驯鹿朋友去上货区
- Lawrence！- Hey，Teddy.
- 拉瑞 - 泰迪
Great to see you in one piece.
真高兴看到完整的你
Sakagawea，a little hot wax，and I'm a new man.
莎卡佳薇弄点热腊就黏好了
Larry？
拉瑞？
I told you I wasn't making fun of you.
我说过我不是跟你开玩笑
- I know。- Teddy？
- 我知道 - 泰迪？
Oh，my God.
老天
Wanna meet her？
你想见见她吗？
- Yeah？- Yeah.
- 想 - 好
Okay，come on.
来吧
Excuse me。President Roosevelt，this is my friend Rebecca.
罗斯福总统 这是我朋友贝嘉
- An honor。- Hi.
- 幸会 - 你好
And this is Sakagawea.
这位是莎卡佳歪
- Wea。- Wea.
- 薇 - 薇
Wea.
薇
I think she has a few questions she wants to ask you.
她有一些问题想问你
You rock。I am a big fan.
你超赞的 我是你的超级粉丝
What would you like to know？
你想知道什么？
Well，I mean，I don't know where to start，but…
我不知道该从何问起
- one Buddha。- Check.
- 达摩祖师 合十答礼 - 到
Two zebras.
两匹斑马
- Right。Check。- Dexter！Welcome back.
- 好 到 - 德克斯特 欢迎回来
Hey，Dex，so look。No hard feelings，all right？
德克斯特 我们和好吧？
- Lawrence！- You saw！
- 拉瑞 - 你看到了
- You saw what he did just then！- Who's evolved？
- 你看到他打我了 - 谁比较高等？
- I am。- Who's evolved？
- 我 - 谁比较高等？
I am！
我！
Good.
很好
Well，they're all here.
全员到齐
Well done。Everyone's in.
干得好 大家都回来了
Yeah，well…
是啊 不过…
…not everyone.
没有全部
We lost a couple of good，little men out there tonight.
我们今晚失去了几个好小子
With great victory comes great sacrifice.
伟大的胜利总是会有些许牺牲
Yeah.
是啊
Dad，look.
爸？你看
Bully！
好耶！
You ain't getting rid of us that easy.
你没那么容易甩掉我们的
Until tomorrow evening，Lawrence？
明晚见？拉瑞
Yeah。I don't know about that，Teddy.
我不知道 泰迪
It's gonna be tough to talk my way out of this one.
这次我可能搞不定了
Well，if that's indeed the case…
若真是那样
…then it's farewell，my friend.
那么就此道别了 朋友
Nick？
尼克？
Your father's a great man.
你父亲是英雄
I know.
我知道
Told you.
我跟你说过了
All right。Good night.
晚安
No，Lawrence。Good day.
不 是早安
Hey，Teddy？
泰迪？
Thanks.
谢了
You're watching New York 1。News all morning.
这是纽约一台 新闻台
Thanks for joining us。There is a fresh blanket of snow.
今天地上铺了一层新雪
But it's not the snow that's got New Yorkers talking.
不过纽约人谈论的可不是这个
It's what's in the snow。There are dinosaur tracks along West 81 st Street.
他们谈的是雪上的东西 西81街上有恐龙脚印
Here's the remarkable video。These appear to be Tyrannosaurus Rex tracks…
那些脚印是暴龙脚印
…and they lead straight to the Museum of Natural History.
足迹直接延伸至自然历史博物馆
Authorities have found what appear to be cave drawings in the subway.
当局发现地铁里有史前洞穴画
Neanderthals atop the museum roof。Elaborate hoax or publicity stunt？
尼安德塔人在博物馆屋顶 这是骗局还是公关活动？
（家庭影片 博物馆之迷）
You be the judge，but one thing's for sure：
由你来决定 但有件事很确定
The folks at the Natural History Museum have really outdone them…
自然历史博物馆的人员 真是使出了浑身绝技
Any explanation at all？
你有何解释？
No。Got nothing.
没 没有解释
Good.
好
I'll take your keys and your flashlight.
我要拿回你的钥匙和手电筒
Folks，this way.
大家 跟我来
My name is Nick Daley。My career Day parent is my dad.
我叫尼克达理 我的职场父母要介绍的是我爸
He's the night watchman at the Museum of Natural History.
他是自然历史博物馆的夜班警卫
Hey，how's it going？Well，Nicky said it：
尼克说过了
I'm the night watchman at the Museum of Natural History.
我是自然历史博物馆的夜班警卫
Let me tell you something：That's when history comes alive.
在那里 历史栩栩如生
How many of you guys have been over to the museum？
你们有多少人到过那里？
Goal！
得分！
Hey，it's getting late。Are you ready to go home？
嘿 时间晚了 你要回家了吗？
Nope.
还没
Let's ride.
冲啊
It was nice of Larry not to rat us out，but this is ridiculous.
拉瑞很好心没举发我们 不过这太扯了
we're night watchmen，not janitors！
我们是夜班警卫 不是清洁工
Gentlemen，you're doing a terrific job.
你们好好干
I'll gonna catch a few Z's.
我去打个盹
You ain't going nowhere.
你不能走
Start mopping，hot dog.
快给我拖地
over here.
这边